In the previous lesson, we explained what
marketing means in professional services
and why reputation and relationships
drive revenue.
In this lesson, we'll describe the
marketing mix and apply the seven Ps
services model to an advisory offer.
Every marketing decision a firm makes can
be grouped into a small set of levers.
Traditionally, these were captured as the
four Ps: product, price, place, and
promotion.
Product is what the firm offers.
Price is what it charges.
Place is how the offer reaches the
client.
Promotion is how the firm communicates
its value.
These four levers were designed for
companies selling physical products.
For an advisory firm, they capture only
part of the picture, because the product
is a service delivered by people.
To market services well, three further
levers are added: people, process, and
physical evidence.
Together with the original four, these
make up the seven Ps services mix.
People matter because, in advisory work,
the people are the service.
Process matters because clients judge how
an engagement is run, not just its
outcome.
Physical evidence matters because
intangible work needs tangible proof,
such as credentials, case studies, and
reports.
Think of a restaurant.
The meal is the product, but the service,
the atmosphere, and the way each course
arrives shape the experience just as
much.
Professional services work the same way.
For an advisory firm, the most powerful
levers are usually people, process, and
physical evidence, rather than price or
place.
A firm differentiates through the calibre
of its teams, the rigour of its methods,
and the quality of its credentials.
These are the levers a partner can
actually pull to win and keep work.
For FinSage, the seven Ps reveal a blind
spot.
The firm competes hard on its services
and fees, but pays little attention to
how it presents its people and past work.
Strengthening its physical evidence, such
as sharper case studies, could raise its
win rate without changing its prices.
Let's stop the lesson here.
In this lesson, we first described the
classic four Ps.
We then saw how the seven Ps extend the
mix for services.
Finally, we applied the mix to an
advisory firm.
In the next lesson, we'll examine the
characteristics that make services
different from products.