Lesson 6: Emergence.
In this lesson, we'll define 'emergence'
and explain why emergent outcomes are
difficult to predict in advance.
Emergence refers to behaviours or
outcomes that arise from the interactions
between the different parts of a system.
The system produces something that none
of its components could produce in
isolation.
Take "team culture". The individual
members of a team do relatively discrete
things: they communicate in certain ways,
they respond to requests within certain
timeframes, they handle conflict using
particular patterns.
None of them individually creates a
culture.
Yet from the accumulation of those
interactions over time, something arises
which we recognise as a team's character.
That character is emergent; no single
person designed it and no policy mandated
it.
The same dynamic operates at an
organisational level.
When a firm develops a reputation for
being the most responsive in its market,
it didn't come from any one person's
behaviour.
It emerged from a pattern of interactions
across the organisation over time,
reinforced by structures, incentives, and
norms that nobody sat down to design.
So, if we understand emergence, why does
it consistently surprise us? The answer
lies in how we tend to explain outcomes;
we explain them by pointing to
components.
When something goes well, we look for the
person who made it happen. When something
goes wrong, we look for whoever caused
it.
However, in complex systems, many of the
most significant outcomes aren't
traceable to any individual component;
they emerge from the interactions between
them.
When we understand that emergence can't
be traced to a single cause, we can
respond to it more effectively.
The shift systems thinking asks us to
make, when we encounter surprising or
undesirable outcomes, is from "who caused
this?" to "what produced this?"
The shift is toward understanding the
structural conditions that made the
outcome more likely. Asking "who caused
this" almost always leads us to an
individual.
That individual may well have contributed
to the outcome, but if we stop there,
we've addressed a symptom and left the
structural conditions unchanged.
The next person in that role will face
the same conditions and produce a similar
result. Asking "what produced this" leads
us to the interactions, the incentive
structures, the feedback loops, and the
delays that shaped the outcome.
Those are the things that, if addressed,
will change what the system produces.
This shift applies across team dynamics,
organisational strategy, and professional
practice of all kinds.
Let's stop the lesson here.
In this lesson, we first defined
emergence as behaviour that arises from
interactions rather than from individual
components.
We then examined why emergence surprises
us.
Finally, we introduced the shift from
individual blame to structural analysis
as a core discipline of systems thinking.