Welcome to this course on connecting AI
agents to systems
So far most of us have used AI to answer
questions and generate content. In this
course, we'll learn how AI can act on our
systems for us — and how to connect it
safely.
In this first lesson, we'll explain what
it means to connect an AI agent to a
system, and why it's more than just
adding a feature.
Up to now, most of us have used AI in one
mode: we ask, and it answers. We type a
question or paste a document, and we read
the response.
In that mode, the AI sits outside our
systems. It has no hands. A person still
has to take whatever it produces and
carry it into the real workflow.
An AI agent is different. An agent
doesn't just produce text for a person to
act on. It acts.
Given access, it can read a record,
update a field, or trigger the next step
in a process. The AI model is still at
the centre, deciding what to do.
What's new is that it's given tools and
connections that let it reach into our
live systems and change them.
That, in a sentence, is what connecting
means: giving an AI the tools to act, not
just answer.
That difference, between answering and
acting, is what this course is about.
Once an AI can act, and not just
describe, it matters a great deal where
we let it act, where we don't, and who
stays in control.
It's tempting to treat connecting an
agent as a technical detail that comes
after the real decisions are made.
Connecting an agent doesn't just make one
step faster. It changes who does the
work, what the process can do on its own,
and how information moves through it.
A step that used to wait for a person can
now run by itself. A check that used to
happen in someone's head now happens in
code. An action that used to need a
signature can now happen automatically.
Those are real changes to how the process
behaves, and they affect the steps before
and after, not just the one we touched.
So the worst way to connect an agent is
to put it into whatever step seems
convenient, without a plan, and see what
happens.
The better way is to decide, in advance,
exactly where the agent acts, what it's
allowed to touch, and where a person
stays in control.
That's why we start not from the
technology but from a map of the work,
even a rough one.
A map is just a clear picture of how a
process runs, with a few points marked:
where an agent could add value, where it
must not be allowed to decide, and where
a person stays in control.
This course is about taking one of those
points and turning it into a real,
working, governed connection.
In this course, we'll cover three things.
First, how an agent actually connects to
a system, through tools, A.P.I's, and the
Model Context Protocol.
Second, how to judge where a connection
is safe and where it carries real risk,
by separating what an agent reads from
what it can change, and limiting its
access carefully.
Third, how to build oversight and
resilience into the connection, and then
take it safely into live operation.
By the end, we'll be able to take a
single candidate point on a process map
and produce a complete connection design:
the tools it needs, the access it's
allowed, the checkpoints around it, and
the way it fails safely.
Let's stop the lesson here.
In this lesson, we first explained what
connecting an AI agent actually means:
giving it the tools to act on our
systems, not just answer questions.
We then saw why that changes how a
process works, not just how fast it runs,
which is why we plan a connection from a
map rather than improvising it.
Finally, we outlined what we'll build
together: a complete, governed connection
design for one part of a process map.