Lesson 8 – Monitoring Vendor Performance.
In this lesson, we’ll monitor vendor
performance and contract compliance
during project execution. <break
time="0.5s" />
Once vendor work is underway, the project
needs to make sure it’s delivered as
agreed.
Monitoring vendor performance helps the
project confirm that work meets contract
requirements and supports the approved
plan.
It also allows issues to be identified
early, before they become bigger
problems.
This is a core part of maintaining
control in predictive projects. <break
time="0.5s" />
Vendor performance is monitored by
comparing actual work against what was
agreed in the contract.
This includes checking whether
deliverables meet quality standards, are
completed on time, and stay within agreed
cost limits.
Reviews may take place at key milestones
or at regular intervals, depending on the
contract.
The goal is not to manage how the vendor
does the work.
The goal is to confirm that outcomes meet
expectations.
Monitoring performance also means
monitoring contract compliance.
The project checks that the vendor is
following agreed terms, such as reporting
requirements, approval processes, and
change procedures.
Any work outside the contract must be
formally approved before it begins.
This protects the project from scope
creep and unplanned costs. <break
time="0.5s" />
In some projects, performance
expectations are also supported by
service level agreements, or SLAs.
These define specific performance
measures, such as response times or
availability levels.
They provide another way to monitor
whether vendor services are being
delivered as agreed. <break time="0.5s"
/>
Projects may use inspections, audits, or
performance reviews to assess vendor
work.
These activities help verify that
deliverables meet acceptance criteria and
that contractual obligations are being
met.
Findings from reviews may result in
corrective actions, approved changes, or
formal updates to the contract.
For example, during a system rollout, the
project reviews a vendor’s deliverable
against the agreed acceptance criteria.
The work meets the technical requirements
but is delivered late, prompting the
project to address schedule performance
while still accepting the output. <break
time="0.5s" />
Let’s stop here.
In this lesson, we focused on how vendor
work is monitored during execution.
We also looked at how projects track
vendor performance, check contract
compliance, and use inspections and
reviews to verify outputs.