Most project teams know what they need to
deliver. Far fewer have agreed on how
they will work together to deliver it.
That gap, between task clarity and
behavioral clarity, is where friction,
confusion, and conflict tend to take
root.
In this course, we'll explore how team
ground rules close that gap, and how to
define, facilitate, document, and sustain
them across a project's full lifecycle.
In this first lesson, we'll distinguish
team ground rules from general project
policies and explain their role in
enabling productive collaboration.
Let's begin with a distinction that's
easy to blur.
A project policy is a formal rule or
procedure: how change requests are
submitted, how risks are escalated, how
budgets are approved.
These exist at the organizational or
project-governance level, and they apply
whether a team agrees with them or not.
Ground rules are different. They are the
behavioral norms a team sets for itself:
how members communicate with one another,
how disagreements are raised, how
decisions get made when there's no single
authority.
They describe how the team will work
together day to day, not just what the
team is expected to produce.
Ground rules are agreed behavioral norms
that govern how a team works together,
distinct from project policies or
governance procedures.
Ground rules are set by the team, for the
team.
Because members participate in creating
them, they carry a sense of shared
ownership that a policy document rarely
achieves.
It's tempting to treat ground rules as a
soft formality, something that gets
mentioned in a kick-off meeting and then
forgotten. But that underestimates what
they actually do.
The first thing they create is
psychological safety.
When a team has agreed norms around how
disagreement is handled, or how quieter
voices get heard, people feel safer
raising problems early.
Research consistently shows that
psychological safety, the belief that
it's safe to speak up without penalty, is
one of the strongest predictors of team
effectiveness.
Ground rules are a practical mechanism
for building that safety into the team's
structure rather than leaving it to
chance.
The second thing they do is reduce
ambiguity.
Without agreed norms, every interaction
carries an implicit question: what are
the rules here?
Is it acceptable to challenge a senior
colleague's estimate in a team meeting?
How quickly is someone expected to
respond to a message?
These questions get answered one way or
another, but without ground rules they're
answered inconsistently, by whoever
happens to have the most social authority
in the moment.
The third thing ground rules do is
support accountability without requiring
conflict.
When a norm has been agreed collectively,
calling it out when it's violated is not
a personal criticism, it's a reference to
a commitment the whole team made.
That shift from personal to collective
accountability changes how difficult
conversations feel for everyone involved.
Teams that skip ground rules don't avoid
the need for norms. They just allow them
to develop informally, which means they
develop unevenly.
Some members assume behaviors that others
find frustrating. Dominant personalities
set precedents that quieter members feel
unable to challenge.
Ambiguity about decision-making authority
gets resolved through whoever escalates
fastest, not through a shared
understanding of the process.
The pattern that tends to follow is a
slow accumulation of small frustrations
that eventually surface as larger
conflicts.
By the time the conflict is visible, it's
carrying the weight of everything that
wasn't said before.
That's a much harder conversation to have
than the one you could have had at the
start.
One last distinction worth making in this
opening lesson: "ground rules" and
"working agreements" are often used
interchangeably, and for our purposes in
this course that's fine.
If there's a nuance, it's this: "ground
rules" tends to emphasize the behavioral
norms themselves, while "working
agreement" tends to refer to the document
that captures those norms in a format the
team can refer back to.
We'll use both terms throughout this
course.
When we talk about the process of
facilitating and defining norms, we'll
generally say "ground rules." When we
talk about the artifact that records
them, we'll say "working agreement.".
In this course, we'll cover what ground
rules are, where they fit in a team's
development, and how to facilitate,
document, and sustain them.
By the end, we'll be able to design and
lead a ground rule-setting process for a
real project team and adapt it for hybrid
or virtual contexts.
In this lesson, we first distinguished
team ground rules from project policies,
establishing that ground rules are
behavioral norms set by the team for the
team.
We then explored why they matter,
covering their role in building
psychological safety, reducing ambiguity,
and enabling collective accountability.
Finally, we introduced the distinction
between ground rules as norms and working
agreements as the documents that capture
them.
In the next lesson, we'll map ground
rule-setting to the right moment in a
team's development, using Tuckman's model
as our guide.