In the previous lesson, we described the
marketing mix and applied the seven Ps
services model to an advisory offer.
In this lesson, we'll identify the four
characteristics of services and explain
how each shapes marketing.
Services behave differently from products
in four important ways.
These are often summarised as
intangibility, inseparability,
variability, and perishability.
Intangibility means a service cannot be
seen or touched before it is bought.
Inseparability means it is produced and
consumed at the same time.
Variability means its quality can change
from one engagement to the next.
Perishability means unused capacity, such
as an idle consultant's time, cannot be
stored for later.
Each characteristic creates a distinct
challenge.
Because services are intangible, clients
struggle to judge quality in advance, so
the firm must offer reassurance.
Because they are inseparable, the
client's experience of the team becomes
part of the product itself.
Variability raises the risk of
inconsistent delivery, which can damage a
hard-won reputation.
Perishability means a firm must keep its
people productive, since time that goes
unsold is lost revenue.
Firms manage these challenges
deliberately.
To counter intangibility, they make the
work tangible through credentials, case
studies, and a strong brand.
To manage variability, they standardise
their methods and invest in training, so
quality holds steady across teams.
These responses turn the characteristics
of services from a weakness into a source
of trust.
FinSage feels perishability most keenly.
When its pipeline is thin, experienced
advisors sit idle, and that time can
never be recovered.
A clearer view of its market, which we'll
build later in the course, would help
FinSage keep its people consistently
deployed.
Let's stop the lesson here.
In this lesson, we first identified the
four characteristics of services.
We then examined the challenge each one
creates.
Finally, we saw how firms respond to
them.
In the next lesson, we'll turn to the
core principles of marketing for advisory
firms.