Lesson 1: A Different Way of Thinking.
In this course, we'll explore systems
thinking, a discipline that helps us see
complexity more clearly and make better
decisions as a result.
In this first lesson, we'll explain what
systems thinking is and contrast it with
linear, cause-and-effect reasoning.
Let's begin with an example.
A customer service team is under
pressure.
Complaints are piling up and response
times are slipping.
The obvious solution seems clear: hire
more staff. For a few weeks, things
improve.
Six months later however, the complaint
backlog is back, and this time it's
larger.
So, what went wrong?
The problem is linear thinking. Linear
thinking follows a simple chain: problem
leads to cause, cause leads to fix.
It works well for problems that are
genuinely simple and isolated, like a
broken piece of equipment, or a single
missing piece of data.
However, most professional problems
aren't like this. They involve multiple
actors, competing pressures, and outcomes
that take time to surface.
When we apply linear thinking to those
kinds of problems, we often get answers
that are partially right in the short
term but wrong over time, in ways we
didn't anticipate.
In our customer service example, adding
staff reduced visible pressure, and that
reduced pressure changed how leadership
prioritised the underlying problems.
With urgency removed, the root causes of
complaints, that is: unclear processes
and poor handoffs between teams, were
never properly addressed.
The system adapted around the fix, and
the problem returned.
So, how do we know when a problem is
systemic rather than isolated?
There are a few reliable signals.
The first is that the same problem keeps
returning, even after it appears to have
been fixed. If a solution that worked
last year isn't working now, the problem
likely has structural roots that weren't
addressed.
The second signal is that different parts
of the organisation experience the
problem differently, and each blames the
other.
When every team has a reasonable account
of what's going wrong and each account is
at odds with the others, the issue is
almost certainly in the interactions
between those teams, not within any
single one of them.
The third is that well-intentioned
interventions make things worse.
If every fix creates a new problem, the
system is pushing back against the
intervention. That's a strong signal that
the fix isn't addressing the right part
of the system.
Systemic problems are structural, and
can't be resolved with simple fixes.
To tackle systemic problems, we'll use
'systems thinking'.
Systems thinking is a discipline that
focuses on structures, relationships, and
patterns of behaviour over time, rather
than on individual events and single
causes.
'Systems thinking' is an extension of
'analytical thinking'.
Where analytical thinking asks "what
happened?", systems thinking asks "what
keeps producing this?" Where analytical
thinking isolates a variable, systems
thinking looks at the web of connections
around it.
It's worth being clear about what systems
thinking is not. It isn't a method for
analysing every possible variable in a
situation. And it isn't about building
elaborate diagrams before we're allowed
to act.
It's a practical discipline, and the
vocabulary it uses is accessible to any
professional willing to look at problems
differently.
In this course, we'll define what a
system is and examine its structural
building blocks: stocks, flows and
feedback loops.
We'll then explore the characteristic
behaviours that complex systems produce
including delays, emergence, and
unintended consequences.
Finally, we'll discuss how to apply a
systems lens to real decisions at work
through mental models, leverage points
and informed action.
By the end, we'll be able to identify
systemic patterns, avoid common
decision-making traps, and frame problems
in ways that lead to more durable
solutions.
Let's stop the lesson here.
In this lesson, we first examined why
linear, cause-and-effect reasoning
struggles when applied to complex
problems.
We then looked at the signals that tell
us a problem is systemic rather than
straightforward.
Finally, we clarified what systems
thinking is and what it isn't.