In the previous lesson, we identified the
four characteristics of services and
explored how each shapes marketing.
In this lesson, we'll explain the core
principles of marketing that apply to
advisory firms.
At the centre of marketing lies a simple
idea: value.
A client engages a firm because they
expect the value of the outcome to exceed
the fee they pay.
For an advisory firm, value rarely comes
from the report itself.
It comes from the decision the client can
now make, the risk they avoid, or the
result they achieve.
Articulating that value clearly is one of
the most important things a firm can do.
A firm captures this in its value
proposition, a clear statement of the
client problem it solves and why it
solves it better than the alternatives.
A weak value proposition lists services.
A strong one names the client's problem
and the outcome the firm delivers.
We'll return to this idea when we look at
positioning later in the course.
Marketing also looks beyond a single
sale.
A client who returns again and again is
worth far more than the first engagement
alone, a principle known as client
lifetime value.
This reframes the economics of the firm.
Winning a new client is expensive, but a
trusted relationship can generate work
for years.
This is why retaining and growing
relationships often matters more than
constant new-client chasing.
FinSage has historically measured success
one project at a time.
Viewed through client lifetime value, its
picture changes.
A handful of long-standing clients
quietly generate most of its revenue,
which suggests where its marketing effort
is best spent.
Let's stop the lesson here.
In this lesson, we first explained the
principle of value and exchange.
We then defined the value proposition.
Finally, we explored why client lifetime
value matters.
In the next lesson, we'll look at how
professional services are actually
bought.